现在我们要看一个非常通用的机制，
叫做Merkle-Damgard机制
So now we're gonna look at a very general
paradigm called the Merkle-Damgard
用于组建抗碰撞的哈希函数
paradigm, that's used for constructing
collision-resistant hash functions. Before
在这之前，我先提示一下我们的目标
we do that, let me just remind you what
our goals are. So as usual we say that H
通常我们说H是个哈希函数，
将大的信息空间映射到小的标签空间
is a hash function that maps some large
message space into a small tag space. And
我们说哈希函数的一个碰撞是一对不同的信息
we say that a collision for a hash
function is basically a pair of distinct
它们正好被哈希函数映射到同样的值
messages that happen to map to the same
value under this hash function. And our
我们的目标是构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
goal is to build collision-resistant hash
functions namely functions where it's hard
对这些函数，即使找一个碰撞也是困难的。
尽管我们知道有很多碰撞存在
to find even a single collision. Even
though we know many collisions exist. No
没有有效的算法可以输出哪怕一个碰撞。
那么我们要构建这些哈希函数
efficient algorithm can even output a
single collision. So we're gonna construct
我们分两步构造这些抗碰撞的哈希函数
these hash functions, these collision
resistant hash functions, in two steps.
第一步，就是我们本节要讲的
The first step, which we're gonna do in
this segment, is to show that if you give
如果给我一个处理短信息的抗碰撞哈希函数，我们可以扩展它
me a collision resistant hash function for
short messages, we can extend it and build
来构建一个处理长得多的信息的抗碰撞的哈希函数
a collision resistant hash function for
much, much, much longer messages. In the
在下一节，我们将构建处理短信息的
next segment, we'll actually build
collision-resistant HASH functions for
抗碰撞的哈希函数。那我们看这个机制
short messages. Okay so let's look at the
construction. The construction is actually
这个机制很通用，事实上所有的抗碰撞的哈希函数
very general and in fact all
collision-resistant hash functions follow
都遵循这个机制。这是一个非常优雅的机制
this paradigm. It's actually a very
elegant paradigm and let me show you how
我告诉大家它的工作过程。这里我们有函数H
it works. So here we have our function H
which we're gonna assume is a
我们假设H是抗碰撞的哈希函数，可以处理短输入
collision-resistant hash function for
small sized inputs. So the way we're gonna
我们使用这个小函数h，h有时叫做压缩函数
use this little function h, this h is
sometimes called a compression function,
我们将取长信息M，把它分成若干分组
is we're gonna take a big message M and
break this message in to blocks. And then
然后我们使用一个固定值叫做IV。这里IV永远是固定的
we use a fixed value called the IV. Here
is the case the IV is fixed forever. And
它内嵌在代码和标准里，只是一个固定的ID
it's basically embedded in the code and in
the standards, it's just a fixed ID that's
是函数的一部分。然后我们对第一个信息分组
part of the fin-nation of the function.
And then what we do is we apply the small
应用小的压缩函数H，一并使用这个ID
compression function H to the first
message block along with this ID. What
得到的叫做链接变量，将被交给下一压缩函数
comes out of that is what's called a
chaining variable that's gonna be fed into
来压缩下一分组，一并使用前一链接变量
the next compression function which
compresses the next block along with the
输出下一链接变量
previous chaining variable and out comes
the next chaining variable, and the next
然后下个信息分组被压缩，等等。。
直到我们到达最后分组
message block is compresses, and so on and
so forth until we reach the final message
在最后分组上，我们要做一个特别的事情
block. And then the final message block,
the one special thing that we do, is that
我们必须这个补齐分组PB(补齐分组之意)附在信息后面
we must append this padding block, this
PB, which stands for padding block (and
我稍后解释这个补齐分组。但在我附上补齐分组之后
I'll explain what the padding block is in
just a second). But after we append the
我们还是要压缩最后的链接变量与最后的分组
padding block we again compress the last
chaining variable with the last message
得到的输出就是实际哈希函数的输出
block, and the output of that is the
actual output of the hash function. So
总结一下，用符号表示，我们有这个压缩函数
just to summarize, in symbols, we have
this compression function that elements in
在T中取元素。这与哈希函数正好相反
T. This is the opposite of the hash
function. Plus message blocks, this x
加上信息分组，这个X对应信息分组，输出下一链接变量
corresponds to message blocks, and outputs
the next chaining variables. So as I said,
如我所说，这就是压缩函数的工作。然后根据这个压缩函数
this is what the compression functions do.
And then from this compression function
我们可以构建一个长输入的哈希函数
we're able to build a hash function for
large inputs, namely inputs is the space x
输入是空间X的L次方，表示至多L个X的分组。
当然这些长度可变
to some power of l namely up to l blocks
of x. And of course these are variable
这样我们可以有不同的信息长度
lengths so we could have different length
messages that are being given input to
它们给函数h输入，得到的是标签空间中的标签
this function h and what comes out of it
is basically a tag in tag space. So the
唯一剩下的需要定义的是补齐分组
only thing left to define is the padding
block. So the padding block is actually
补齐分组非常重要，我们待会将看到
very important as we're gonna see in just
a minute. What it is, is basically, well
这是序列1000，为实际明文分组的结尾
it's a sequence of 1000 that denotes the
end of the actual message block. And then
这个分组最重要的部分是我们对信息长度进行的编码
the most important part of the message
block is that we encode the message length
在这个补齐分组里。信息长度域固定为64位
In this padding block. And the message
length field is basically fixed to be 64
所以在所有的SHA哈希函数中
bits. So in all the SHA hash
functions, so in all the SHA hash
最大的信息长度为2的64次方减一
functions the maximum message length is
two to the sixty four minus one so in fact
事实上信息长度应当适应于64位分组。
2的64次方减一位的信息长度的上界
the message length fits into a 64 bit
block. An upper bound of two to the sixty
对应我们能释放的信息来说足够长了
four minus one bit on the message length
is actually sufficiently long to handle
好，这是补齐分组
all of the messages we're gonna throw at
it. Okay, so that's the padding block, and
当然，问题来了：如果最后一个分组
of course the question is: what do we do
if the last block really is a multiple of
是压缩函数分组长度的倍数，我们怎么办？
我们该如何补齐分组？
the compression function of block length?
Where are we gonna fit the padding block?
通常，答案是如果在最后分组中没有空间
And the answer, as usual, is basically if
there's no space for the padding block in
留给补齐分组时，那么我们就必须加另外一个假分组
the last block of the message, then we're
gonna have to ass another dummy block and
把补齐分组放在那里。当然以正确的方式写1000..
stick the padding block in there. And of
course put the one zero, zero, zero in the
有一点非常重要，那就是
right place. Okay so the point is that
it's very, very important that the padding
补齐分组包含信息长度，我们待会将会看到
block contains the message length as we'll
see in just a minute. So this is the
那么这就是Merkle-Damgard机制，最后一点技术内容
Merkle-Damgard construction, the last
piece of terminology I'll say is that we
是我们有这些链接变量。那么H0是初始值，
H1,H2,H3直到H4
have these chaining variables. So H0 is
the initial value. H1, H2, H3, up to H4
H4是哈希函数的最终输出。如我所说
which is the actual final output of this
hash function. So as I said, all standard
所有的标准哈希函数都遵循着这个机制，
由一个压缩函数，构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
hash functions follow this paradigm for
constructing a collision resistant hash
这个机制如此流行的原因是
function from a compression function. The
reason that this paradigm is so popular is
因为下面这个定理告诉我们
because of the following theorem, which
says basically that if the little
如果小的压缩函数是抗碰撞的
compression function is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
那么大的Merkle-Damgard哈希函数也是抗碰撞的
hash function is also collision resistant.
So, in other words, if we're going to build
换句话说，如果我们要为长输入构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
collision resistant functions for large inputs, all
we have to do is just build compression
我们只需构建一个抗碰撞的压缩函数。
那么我们来证明这个定理
functions that are collision resistant. So
let's prove this theorem. It's a elegant
这个证明很优雅，且不难。我们证它的逆否命题
proof and it's not too difficult. So the
way we're gonna prove it is using the
也就是，如果你能找到这个大哈希函数的一个碰撞
contrapositive, that is, if you can find
me a collision on the big hash function
那么我们可以推出这个小压缩函数的一个碰撞
then we're gonna deduce a collision on the
little compression function. Therefore, if
因此，如果h是抗碰撞的，那么H也是
little h is a collision resistant, so will
be the big H. So suppose you give me a
假设给我一个大压缩函数的碰撞，即两个不同的信息M和M'
collision on the big compression function,
namely two distinct messages M and M',
它们正好被哈希到同一个输出，我们将使用M和M'
that happen to hash to the same output,
we're going to use M and M' to build
来构建这个小压缩函数的一个碰撞
a collision on the little compression
function. So the first thing is we
首先我们必须记住Merkle-Damgard机制的过程
have to remember how the Merkle-Damgard
construction works and, in particular,
特别地，当我们哈希M和M'，给链接变量起一些名字
let's assign names to the chain variables
when we hash M versus when we hash M'.
当我们计算信息M的哈希值时，会得到这些链接变量
So here are the chain variables that come up
when we hash the message M, so H0 is the
那么H0是固定的IV，开启整个过程，H1是
fixed IV that starts the whole process, H1
would be the result of hashing the first
用IV计算第一个分组的哈希结果，等等。。
直到H_t+1是最后一个链接变量
message block with the IV, and so on and
so forth, until H sub t+1 is the
也是Merkle-Damgard链的最后输出
final chain variable, which is the final
output of the Merkle-Damgard chain. And
类似地对于M'，我们定义H0'为第一个链接变量
then similarly for M', let's define H0'
to be the first chaining variable, H1'
H1'是第一个分组M'的压缩结果，等等。。
to be the result after compressing
the first message block of M', and so
直到我们获得H'_r+1，即信息M'的最后哈希值
on and so forth, up until we get to H'
of r+1, which is the final hash of
现在大家注意信息M和M'的长度
the message M'. Now you notice the
length of the messages M and M'
不一定是一样的。特别地，M的长度为t，M'的长度为r
don't have to be the same. In particular, M
has length t, whereas M' has length r.
因为发生了碰撞，我们知道这两个值是一样的
Now because the collision occurred, we
know that these two values here are the
H(M)=H(M')。换句话说，最后的链接变量
same. H(M) is equal to H(M'). In
other words, the last chaining variables
等于另外一个的。现在我们仔细看
are actually equal to one another. So now
let's look carefully how H t+1 and
H_t+1和H'_r+1是如何计算的
H' r+1 were calculated. Well
H t+1 is calculated as the
H_t+1是由压缩函数应用到之前的链接变量
compression function applied to the
previous chaining variable along with the
并使用M的最后分组得到的，包括补齐分组
last message block of M, including the
padding block. You'll notice here I'm
大家注意，我这里假设补齐分组可以放在M的最后分组里
assuming that the padding block fits with
the last message block of M even if the
即使最后的补齐分组在它自己的分组里，
也没有任何的区别
last padding block is in its own block,
it's not going to make any difference. So
为了简便，我们假设补齐分组在M的最后分组里
for simplicity, let's assume that the
padding block fits with the last message
那么，通过计算最后分组的哈希，要用到补齐分组
block with capital M. So, by hashing the
last message block with a padding block
和最后的链接变量，我们获得了H_t+1
and the last chaining variable, we obtain
H t+1 and, similarly, the same thing
类似地也可以对M'做同样的事情。通过
计算最后的信息分组和最后的链接变量的哈希
happens with M'. By hashing the last
message block, the last chaining variable,
我们获得了H'_r+1。我们知道，由于这两个值相等
we obtain H' r+1. And we know
that, since these two values are equal, all
突然间我们有了一个候选的压缩函数的碰撞
of a sudden we have a candidate collision
for the compression function. Here, let me
这里我们圈出这个候选的碰撞，这是一部分，这是另一部分
circle the candidate collision, this is one
part of it and this is the other part of
那么我们有了两个参数之间的一个等式
it. Okay, so we have an equality
between two arguments given to the
这两个参数交给压缩函数，正好产生了同样的输出值
compression function that happen to
produce the same value. The only way we
我们唯一的不获得任何碰撞的方法是，
如果参数正好是一样的
would not get a collision is if the
arguments happen to be the same. In other
换句话说，这里我们看到，如果压缩函数的参数不同
words, what we're seeing here is if the
arguments to the compression function are
那么我们就获得了h的一个碰撞。我们写得更精确些
distinct, then we get a collision for
little h. So let's write it out more
如果H_t不等于H'_r，或Mt不等于M'r
precisely: so if H t is not equal to H' r,
or Mt is not equal to M' r,
或者补齐分组不同，那么我们得到了压缩函数h的一个碰撞
or the padding blocks are distinct, then
we have a collision for the compression
我们就完成任务了，收工。我们还不能收工的情况是
function h and we're done, we're done and we can stop. So, the only way we need to continue is if
这个三个'或'的条件不成立。三个'或'不成立是什么意思？
this three-way disjunction doesn't hold.
So what does it mean that this disjunction
我们需要继续工作的唯一情况是
doesn't hold? Well, so the only reason we
need to continue is if the second-to-last
当两个倒数第二个链接变量相等，且
两个信息的最后分组也相等，且
chaining variables are equal, the last
blocks of the messages are equal and the
两个信息的补齐分组也相等才行。那么
两个补齐分组相等意味着什么？
two padding blocks are equal. So what does
it mean that the two padding blocks are
记得信息长度被编码在补齐分组里的
equal? Remember that the message lengths
were encoded in the padding block. So, in
特别地，这意味着M的长度和M'的长度一致
particular, this means that the length of M
and the length of M' is the same,
即t=r。那么从现在开始，我可以假设t=r了
namely the t is equal to r. So from now on
I can assume t is equal to r. Whenever I
我写r，相当于是t。但现在我们可以
wrote r, I'm just gonna write t. But now we
can apply exactly the same argument to the
对倒数第二个链接变量应用同样的参数。
换句话说，Ht是如何计算的？
second to last chaining variables. In
other words, how was H t computed? Well
Ht是计算前一个链接变量H_t-1的哈希得到的
H t is computed by hashing the previous
chaining variable, namely H t-1,
用倒数第二个信息分组。类似地，H't也被计算出来
with the second to last message block. And
similarly, H' t was computed, you
大家注意我把r替换成t，那么H't是由前一链接变量
notice I replaced r by t, so H' t was
computed by hashing the previous chaining
用M'的倒数第二个信息分组计算哈希得到
variable along with the second to last
message block of M'. And because
因为这两个值相等，现在我们获得了另一个
候选的压缩函数的碰撞
these two are equal, now we get another
candidate collision for the compression
换句话说，如果H_t-1不等于H'_t-1
function. In other words, if H t-1 is not
equal to H' t-1, or M t-1 is not equal to
或M_t-1不等于M'_t-1，那么我们有一个h的碰撞，收工
M' t-1, then basically we
have a collision for h, and we can stop,
现在，我们需要继续的唯一情况是这个条件不成立
we're done. So now, the only case when we
need to continue is if this condition over
那么我们假设H_t-1等于H'_t-1
here doesn't hold, namely, so let's suppose
that H t-1 is equal to H' t-1
我们已经知道，Mt等于M't
and we already know that, let's
see, so M t is equal to M' t and
且M_t-1等于M'_t-1。假设这两个条件
M t-1 is equal to M' t-1.
Suppose it so happens that these two
正好都成立，大家可以看到，现在我们可以继续迭代
conditions hold, well, you can see that now
we can continue to iterate. In other
换句话说，我们现在可以给H_t-1和H'_t-1应用同样的参数
words, we can now apply exactly the same
argument to H t-1 and H' t-1
那么一次又一次地迭代，我们可以迭代到
and so iterating this again and
again, we can iterate all the way to the
信息的开始。迭代到信息的开始
beginning of the message. Iterate to the
beginning of the message, and one of two
下面两者之一一定成立：我们要不找到压缩函数的碰撞
things must hold, either we find the
collision for the compression function
要不M和M'的所有分组都相同
or it so happens that all the message blocks
of M and M' are the same. In other
换句话说，对所有的i，Mi等于M'i。这意味着
words, for all i, M i is equal to M' i.
But this means, because the messages, we'd
我们已经证明了两个信息的长度相同，这意味着M=M'
reprove the messages are the same length,
this means that M is actually equal to M'.
然而，这与给我的是个碰撞的前提相矛盾
But then, this contradicts the fact
that you gave me a collision to begin
换句话说，这里的前提不能发生
with, so, in other words, this condition
over here, can't actually happen because
因为它与M和M'是这个大Merkle-Damgard
函数H的碰撞的事实相矛盾
it contradicts the fact that M and M'
are actually a collision for the big
因此，这意味着我们必须为这个压缩函数
Merkle-Damgard function H. And, as
a result, this means that we have to find a
找到一个碰撞。我们从信息的最后开始工作
collision for the compression function, so
that, as we work our way from the end of
一路算到信息开头，在某处我们一定可以找到h的碰撞
the message, all the way to the beginning,
at some point we must find the collision
这就完成了我们的证明
for little h. Okay, so this basically
completes the proof of the theorems, I can
我可以在这里写个"证毕"了，这就是证明
put a little Q.E.D block here, so basically
what this proof is, that if the little
(Q.E.D = quod erat demonstrandum 拉丁文)
如果压缩函数h是抗碰撞的
compression function h is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
则大Merkle-Damgard函数H也必须是抗碰撞的
function H must also be collision
resistant. So, again, the reason why people
人们之所以喜欢这个机制，是因为这个定理
展示了如何构建大的哈希函数
like this construction is it shows that
to construct big hash functions,
只要能构建短输入的压缩函数就足够了
it suffices to construct just compression
functions for small inputs, and we're
我们下一节看如何构建压缩函数
gonna do that in the next segment.